Okay, so welcome guys, so this is our call with Bianca from Overhaul Health and
Wellness,
is that how is that how we say it?
Yeah, that's it.
And Bianca is a health and transformation coach, have I got that right as well?
Yep, absolutely.
So you're coming to talk to us today about something that quite a few of our
men are
members asked about, which is empowerment through nutrition.
So I know that there's potentially a few vegans in our group who are asking for
you vegan-based
questions, but also we want to know a lot about feeling happier and healthier
and feeling
empowered when ourselves through our nutrition.
And I think you're going to talk us through that, aren't you Bianca?
Yeah, absolutely.
If you've got any questions, please just interject and jump in.
That's no problem.
Also, if anyone's got any questions, everyone is more than welcome to follow up
with me outside
of this any other time, so I'm sure you'll be able to give them my contact
details if
anyone has any questions at all.
We'll leave Bianca's contact details underneath this video so that you can
click on them and
get in touch with her if you find questions or you'd like to hear what we're
doing.
Let's go ahead, Bianca.
Beautiful.
Okay, so now I just need to share my screen.
This one.
Okay, can you see my presentation?
Yeah.
Beautiful.
Alright, probably should have started from the beginning from the first screen.
Okie dokie, are we ready?
Yes.
Fabulous.
Awesome.
So welcome along.
Thank you so much for joining me.
I very much appreciate you being here.
This is super exciting, very exciting for me.
I am a plant-based predominant health coach, however, empowerment through
nutrition is
something that's right up my alley.
I love talking about how women can feel empowered, not necessarily just for
nutrition, but in
every aspect and area of their lives.
So when you tie it into nutrition, which is something that I am massively
passionate
about as well, I jumped at the opportunity and I was like, "Yes, I want to do
this.
I want to be here."
So welcome along and thank you so much for joining me.
So with the slideshow that I've got for you today, I'll just want to briefly
run through
what we're going to be looking at so I can kind of pre-frame you so you know
exactly what's
coming and how much is coming.
So there is quite a lot here.
I would recommend grabbing a piece of paper and a pen or at least re-watching
this afterwards
and taking away any sort of information that is quite relevant to you because
we'll be covering
a fair amount as well.
So I'll start off by kind of explaining the definition of empowerment and
nutrition.
When this comes up, you'll be like, "Oh yeah, that's probably why I should talk
about it."
Not to sound patronizing, but it was really interesting to actually pinpoint
the full definition
of empowerment and nutrition because it just works beautifully hand in hand.
Then I'll talk about who the fuck I am, by the way, so I'm not this random
stranger talking
to you.
I want to discuss your body's natural language.
Everybody has its own language and it's just a matter of tapping into yours to
figure out
what it's saying to you, what's it screaming out to you, and how can you talk
back?
And then we'll talk about how to reconnect with your body through a little
acronym that
I call NADA.
We'll talk about what your cravings say about you and how to manage them.
I know talking about cravings was on the top of someone's list here, so it
would be nice
to find out whether that helps, whether this helps with them as well.
Talking about how to eat consciously and centrally for pleasure.
We are all about pleasure.
We are all about enjoying life and what it has to offer, so why not enjoy
nutrition at
the same form of pleasure as well.
How to eat foreign powerment, why choose a plant-based lifestyle, tips to go
plant-based.
As you can see, not a huge amount of this is about, it's focused on plant-based
and veganism.
So like I said, if you have any questions, please by all means, shoot them
through.
I am more than happy to answer anything that you've got for me.
And then for those of you that are able to stick around, I have a freebie and
some special
offers for you folks and I think the girls will be dropping those links in
there as well
so you don't need to worry about scribbling that down.
So for some reason I can't use the keyboard, there we go, so who am I?
I can tell you I'm not a natural poser.
This photo on the right hand side literally took me, literally took me about 32
attempts.
It was ridiculous and if I had a photographer there, they probably would have
just walked
out.
So I'm not a natural poser, so any photos that you might see of me, it is very
difficult
for me to pose.
And I'm not a PowerPoint pro.
I just wanted to pre-frame you on that one because there will be no animations,
no funny
noises or anything, nothing coming in from the left and right, it's just you
get what
you get.
But I'm also a certified health and life coach through health coach Institute.
So I did this back in 2020, I became certified and that's when I pretty much
fell in love
with coaching.
I fell in love with nutrition before that.
But then I found coaching when I found health coach Institute and it just kind
of developed
into this beautiful passion that I have and that I enjoy doing day to day.
I'm a plant-based expert, I have been plant-based myself for about two years
now and it has taken
me a while to hone in and figure out exactly how to live healthfully, how to
live an empowered
life through plant-based nutrition, but that's why I'm here because it's taken
me so long
I want to give everyone the shortcut way to get there.
So I love being plant-based, I love the results that it's given me, I come back
quicker from
the gym, I bounce back, I'm able to build muscle and build the body that I
enjoy, that
I am comfortable in, I'm able to feel satiated, I have less cravings, I don't
know if any
of you have had massive cravings or carbs or bread I think we were just talking
about
there, sugary sweets, whatever it is, I'm able to curb my cravings a lot with
food, I mean
some people are like okay if you're craving food just go for a walk, I'm like n
ah, if
I'm craving food I want to eat.
So that's something that I can do and enjoy through living a plant-based
lifestyle as well.
I am ex-hostility, so I have been in hospitality for 12 years, it's been a long
12 years and
let me tell you, it's a very toxic lifestyle and place to be in.
I was drinking a lot, I was super hungover a lot and my eating habits were just
completely
thrown out the window.
I would be working eight to 12 hours without a break, when I had a break I'd be
shoving
literally truffle fries in my face, I think I did that for about two years when
I worked
in New Zealand, sounds great but it really wasn't on my health, my energy, my
focus,
I literally slept for three hours during the day every day for at least a year
because
I was so drained, I was so exhausted, I wasn't eating the right foods, I was
binge cycling,
so I'd be so hungover, I wouldn't eat because I would be feeling so nauseous or
I would
eat a ridiculous amount, I'd eat fry-ups and drink more the next day.
So it was this vicious cycle of either just not eating at all or eating the
right foods,
not eating the right foods at all or just over eating.
So it was this vicious cycle, I never felt comfortable in my body, I never felt
happy,
never felt like I had any natural form of energy, it was all caffeinated or su
gary beverages,
it just wasn't a great place to be in and that's really what propelled me to
move forward,
to improve my health and get ahold of myself really, get a grip of myself.
So I'm a survivor, so basically what happened when I was in New Zealand, I had
a snowboard
in accident, so I had to pull it forward, rolled forward a few times, stopped,
landed
and I was like, "Oh crap, there's something really wrong", they took me to the
medical
centre, I was in excruciating pain and they flew me off on the helicopter to
the nearest
hospital, "Thanks Rave me", and they said, "Look, right, okay, you've got two
options,
you either go for surgery, which has a 50% chance of survival or you will die
now from
internal bleeding".
So I obviously took the procedure, went home and had about three months' worth
of recovery
and I was bored out of my mind, I was bored shitless, so I was like, "Right,
what do I
do?"
I started watching a few Netflix documentaries and that's what kind of tweaked
my interest
in nutrition.
From there, I created like a 20 page document because I was so bored, I created
a 20 page
document for my step mum to help I lose weight, she still uses that to this day
and that
was in 2015 and I just kind of accumulated all my learning and this passion and
this passion
for nutrition grew and grew and grew, which is where I found Health Coach
Institute became
a qualified coach and basically that's where I am today, so my plant-based
journey kind
of started back then when I had the accident because I decided to cut out meat,
but I was
pescatarian for five years until I kind of hit the nail on the head and I was
like,
"No, I need this, I need to be plant-based, I need to feel more energised
because this
is just not enough and I need to feel empowered."
So that is basically where I have come from and just to let you know, I am a
strong firm
believer in balance.
I do not eat salads every single day of the week, I do not train every single
day of the
week, I definitely party on weekends, most weekends, I drink and I party and I
go out
and I enjoy myself, I am a firm believer that there is a beauty and there is
possibility
to live a balanced lifestyle.
So I wanted to talk briefly about empowerment because like I said, this line
just fitted
so well, so beautifully, so it says the process of becoming stronger and more
confident, especially
in controlling one's life and claiming one's rights and if that's not what we
all want,
I do not know what is and imagine being able to tie that in with nutrition, so
the process
of providing or obtaining the food necessary for health and growth.
Just a key element I want to feed in here is nutrition and food are quite
different,
in 2022 we associate food, well our brains have associated food with a form of
care.
So now, as I will talk about a little bit later, we often use food as a form of
socialising
to fulfil boredom, to fill in for emotions or voids that are happening in our
life and
food is pretty much in and around everything that we do and it is based on
everything that
we do, whereas nutrition is just what your body needs to feel and live its best
self.
So it's just important to kind of separate those and go, hang on a minute, I'm
going
to eat for fuel, I'm going to eat for nutrition, I'm not going to eat food
because it's there
or because social norms tell me I need to eat it, there's just quite an
interesting
mindset shift there.
So reconnecting to your body, do you know your body's natural language because
I certainly
didn't before I started this whole health coaching business.
So your body has its own natural language and it tells you what it needs but we
have
grown a disconnect between understanding and feeling.
So we feel or see, we listen to the language but we don't actually know what it
means.
So the language that your body is talking can be in hunger and fullness cues
for example,
very basic, your stomach starts rumbling, it's telling you and you need to seek
nourishment.
So hunger and fullness to tell you when to seek nourishment and when to stop
eating,
it can come up in cravings so it will tell you or tells us what we're missing.
So a craving might relate to something that you're deficient in, which we'll
come to later.
Inflammation aches and pains in your body can pretty much relate to something
that we
are deficient in as well or something that we are eating too much of.
So inflammation can come from eating too much sugar for example or too much fat
.
And if we're eating too much of that, that is how it shows.
Stress reactions to let us know that life is becoming unmanageable.
A perfect prime example, I'm going to throw myself under the bus here, I've
been taken
on a lot recently and I had a migraine the other day and I had to spend all day
in bed.
That is a stress reaction and I know it is and it's a stress reaction in my
body telling
me that life is becoming unmanageable and that's my body saying Bianca, slow
the fuck
down, chill.
It can come up as insomnia to show us that we have unresolved business and it
can come
up in deeper behavioural, neural connections that your brain has created, which
I was mentioning
earlier, such as unconscious eating.
So that could be eating without the intent of nourishment.
So eating without the intent of nourishment, as I was mentioning to you earlier
, is pretty
much a form of self soothing, distraction from unpleasant sensations and
emotions, avoiding
experiences or challenges in life, changing the level of stimulation, so maybe
when you're
bored, you might need calming down, you might need to regulate your nervous
system, but
sometimes we will relate that to food or if you're feeling overwhelmed, then it
can come
up as managing difficult situations or feelings and it could be a coping
mechanism and a solution
to another problem.
So for this example here, sorry I get my words out, for this example here, what
's happened
is our body has and our brain has been talking and one day you have decided
that you need
soothing, maybe something with around like some bag of crisps or some ice cream
or whatever
is in your environment that you like, okay, so we need to be soothed, we are
feeling uncomfortable
in our situation or something's coming up that we're feeling discomfort, right?
We reach for the food, what happens then is your brain connects the two
together and
says, okay, when I'm feeling that, I need to eat that, I need to seek something
rich
and heavy or salty and fatty and that's what happens with cravings and
unconscious eating.
It's not your fault at all, it's just the way that your brain is conditioning
you and
protecting you from feeling uncomfortable, feeling from those difficult
situations.
So why is learning this language empowering?
Well imagine having the ability, the authority and the knowledge to reduce and
slow aging,
to reduce, prevent and reverse disease and illness, to cure pain and
inflammation in
your body.
Imagine having the ability to control your weight and mood consistently without
feeling
out of control or without feeling the peer pressure and imagine having the
ability, the
authority and the knowledge to gift yourself with energy and time, day after
day.
You get to have the power and authority over your current and future health and
happiness.
I want you to know that and nothing could be more empowering than you deciding
what
happens to your body and your time.
So moving on from that, so let's reconnect to our body.
Taking empowered action with Nada, this is a little acronym that I made up for
my coaching
practice and it starts with noticing patterns in unwanted behaviour.
That's just the first step, notice, I'm eating, I didn't want to eat again, it
's not dinner
time, it's not lunch time, analyzing potential reasons behind choosing these
actions.
So I'm probably bored or I'm actually not feeling so great, so you're analyzing
the
potential reasons.
Then you can decide on a different action which will have you feeling empowered
as opposed
to disempowered and then you can act from an empowered and conscious mindset
versus an
unempowered unconscious state, does that make sense?
I don't even know, I can't even see anyone else's screen, I can't even see
anyone else's
face, I'm literally just looking at my presentation, I don't know how I've
gotten rid of all the
cameras but I can't see anyone's faces.
I will carry on, I hope that makes sense, come on, next one, beautiful, so let
's look
at that in practice.
You can notice, so with another you've got notice, so maybe I'm eating when I'm
not
even hungry, you analyze, okay, well I'm waiting for the next task of the day,
I'm probably
bored, decide, I'm going to decide to wait for lunch to eat because I don't
need to eat
right now, I'm not hungry, I don't need nourishing and then you act, so maybe I
'm going to take
a 10 minute walk instead of eating.
So using that nada is quite useful, to get you out of that habit, it's pretty
much something
that I use with my clients on a one-to-one basis, especially with binge eating
as well,
just anywhere where you feel a little bit disempowered, a little bit out of
control,
and a little bit stuck, really, you can use this however you wish, so I've got
a little
task thing down there, but I know there's not a huge amount of you girls here
today,
so what I'll probably do is let you pause in a minute and notice where this
happens in
your life, so grab your piece of paper and I want you to write down an action
that might
happen in your life that you're not necessarily happy with, so it could be
eating, it could
be being stressed all the time, you know, it doesn't have to be related to food
, anywhere
that you don't feel as empowered or as in control of yourself, right, or your
life,
and then I want you to analyse what could be wrong, so could it be that you're
doing
these things to feel avoid or to soothe an emotion, are you doing it to satisfy
someone
else?
That's always a goody.
I had a client who kind of had this realisation with me that she was
continuously doing stuff
to make her mum happy, and to make her mum proud of her, and she didn't realise
it,
and she noticed the behaviour, she analysed it and she said, 'Oh wait, I'm
doing this
to make my mum feel happy', and she decided to take an empowered action that
made her
feel good, okay granted it didn't make her mum feel good, but that's because
she wasn't
people pleasing anymore, and she acted from a much stronger place of
empowerment, so you
know, it doesn't have to be related to food, it can be related to any area of
your life,
so I just invite you now, if you're watching this back, to pause this and grab
a piece
of paper, and right out where you might see this happen in your life.
Can I end?
Can I ask you something?
Sorry.
No, no, no, like I said, please interrupt, I can't see any faces, so even if
you put
your hand up, I wouldn't have been able to see.
I'm in the bath at the minute, so it's the only quiet time I get for my kids.
One thing I do that's really a weird eating habit is I will wake up in the
middle of the
night, normally about four o'clock, and I haven't got a particularly sweet
tooth, so
I don't often eat sweet stuff, even after dinner, and I'm not massive sweet
tooth kind
of person, but I will wake up and I will need cake or chocolate, to the point
now where
people laugh and they're like, "Oh, Sammy's weird eating habits, I'll take food
to bed
with me, because I'll know it like 4 or 5 a.m., that's what I need."
The only thing I can link it to is I used to wake up when I smoked and have a f
ag at that
time, so I used to wake up every morning because my partner at the time's alarm
was
used to go off, so I'd get up, have a cup of tea, have two fags and go back to
bed.
I don't smoke anymore, but I now wake up and just, it's insane, like I have to
have
sweet stuff, all my family will laugh about it, like, "Oh, Sammy will take a
cake home
or I'll put in home at my mum's for dinner," they'll know that I'll take that
home to
eat in the morning. Sorry, 4 a.m. Snack? Yeah, I can't really work out why or
what it is,
but it doesn't bother me, I just wondered if you had any insight to that.
Yeah, absolutely. So, two things that are coming straight to mind, straight
away, Sammy,
is that one, it most likely has a connection to do with your sleep. So, when we
fridge
raid, when we wake up with a hankering for some food, generally sweet things,
it's because
our sleep has been affected negatively. So, it could mean that you have a poor
nighttime
routine, it could mean that you're not getting enough sleep, it could mean that
your sleep
hygiene needs cleaning up. So, to me, straight off the bat, I would love to
kind of experiment
with you and figure out what actually is the trigger. So, number one, I would
be thinking
of cleaning up the sleep. I don't think very well. How much sleep do you think
you would
get in one go? In one go? Two, three hours? Okay, and all together throughout a
night?
Six, seven? Yeah, okay. So, if we under sleep, just as much as if we oversleep,
we are significantly
increasing our chances of... Another thing that I do with sleep is I'll have,
so in a week,
I'll have sort of five nights where I'll sleep for like between three and five
hours a night
and then I'll have one big sleep and then maybe like a better one night sleep,
but that'll
kind of be my seven day pattern. So, sleeping me and not friends, to be honest.
I do have
a bad sleep routine. And when you're... When we're severely tired, depleted,
two or three
hours isn't enough to get enough good quality sleep as well. Yeah. So, yeah,
straight off
the bat could definitely tell you that you need to work on your sleep early.
Definitely
getting between seven to nine hours is what is recommended. Right? That's quite
a lot getting...
Yeah, it is. And for most of us, I mean, it's 2022. We don't have time to sleep
. We've got lives,
we've got businesses, you know, we've got shit today. I was just thinking... I
don't get everything
done on nine hours sleep annoying. No, I know, exactly, exactly. But it is
recommended that we get
seven to nine hours sleep. Right? If we get under seven hours sleep, which you
're getting,
especially broken, you are severely increasing your chances of many different
side effects,
including heart attack. Yeah. And that includes as well people who obviously
who exceed nine hours
when people get nine to 12 hours. I don't know who does that. Which I'll do one
night a week.
One night, yeah. That would be my big sleep. And I'll think, oh, I've got one
big sleep,
I'm fine now. Well, now you know, I think you think that big sleep, seven
nights a week, right?
Yeah. Okay. So, yeah, I would definitely say that your sleep has something to
do with it.
When we are sleep deprived, we release something hormone called ghrelin, which
is what has us go
in. Oh, I need food. I'm hungry. I'm picky. I need a snack. So, in the middle
of the night,
not only have, so the second branch I was going to say is you've created that
habit, right?
You've created a habit by waking up when your partner's alarm went off, you had
the cigarette,
you had the caffeine, caffeinated beverage, the tea, right? That was creating a
habit.
And regardless of whether it's a good habit or a bad habit, those habits stick
because our brains
like routine. So not only have you created a habit of waking up in the middle
of the night,
now, because you are sleep deprived and chronically sleep deprived, I would
guess,
your brain is going, your gut and your brain are talking and your gut's going,
actually,
I need, I need to eat because I'm feeling really tired and I need, I need to
pick me up.
So I would say it's a combination of me now for five years. And I have not
smoked for five years
this October. So that's, that's quite a long time to keep the same habit, but
you still get up.
Yes. Yeah. Every single night, exactly the same, there's no change. Like, I
used to think,
like the first year, I'd be like, Oh, it's because I've not spoken, these no
longer here,
but I'm used to like waking up to that alone. I'm like five years later down
the line and I still
do the exact same thing. Yeah. Exactly. And I mean, you've probably seen or
heard people who get up
religiously for work at five o'clock AM, for example, on the weekend, if you
speak to them,
they'll be like, you'll be like, did you have a nice lay in? And they'll be
like,
no, my body woke me up at five AM. You know, that's going to be the same for
you as well now,
because it's been so long that at five AM, your body wakes you up. Yeah,
straight away,
regardless. And then you're woken up and you're sleep deprived. So then your
brain goes,
ah, growling. There we go. And then all of a sudden you go, wait, no, I need
something. I need
something sugary. I need it. I need to, I need to, I need to take. I need cake
in my face. Exactly.
Definitely me. That's why they end. Absolutely. So, I mean, just to quickly
wrap up this, I mean,
what I would recommend you doing is start by looking and establishing a
nighttime routine.
So just try and give yourself at least 20 minutes, half an hour routine, at
least before you go to
bed, really clean up that nighttime routine and get your brain and your body
into that rhythm of
going to bed and going to sleep. And it's not going to just, you know, five
years minimum,
it's been five years minimum, right? Of this habit. Yeah, it's been about 10
years. I've been
doing this for, oh my goodness. Yeah. So 10 years, 10 years is a long time to
create
and pretty much instill this habit. So it will take a long time. But if you are
wanting to help
increase that, yeah, maybe I'll talk to you at the end door or after or
whatever, when
so I'm not interrupted too much more of everyone's time. No, no, no, that's
okay. But, but I'm glad
you bring this up because a lot of people get up in the middle of the night and
just go straight
to the fridge and then they're like, why am I here? But yeah, it's a very
important thing
to note is if your sleep is out of whack, if you're sleep deprived, that's why
we rate the
fridge at that time of night. So yeah, clean up your sleep pattern, clean up
your sleep hygiene,
create and establish a good nighttime routine and start getting into the habit
of forcing
yourself to stay in bed. Okay, stay in bed. It's difficult. I know. But yeah,
there's so many
things that you could work on to to decrease that hankering and that need to
grab cake in the
middle of the night. But yeah, we can take that over. Yeah, lovely. Thank you
so much. Oh, you're
very welcome. Please interrupt me again. Like I said, I can't see anyone's
hands up or anything like that.
Beautiful. Okay, so talking about cravings. I know that some people had said
that they wanted
to talk about cravings. So I mean, most of us have crave food. I don't know why
I wrote
have you ever crave the food because most of us have. Was it for something that
was sugary
and cold like ice cream? Was it for something rich and silky like chocolate?
Fatty and cheesy
like pizza? Or maybe you want something crunchy or salty like potato chips or
regular chips?
Well, if you are experiencing that sensation for something sugary and cold or
rich and silky
or cheesy or crunchy or salty, it's likely to be a clue. So your cravings are
clues.
When we can decode our cravings, we can nourish ourselves in a healthy and
satisfying and empowering
way. So get your screenshot buttons ready. I can send this as a photo later. So
I don't really
want to go through all of it because I don't want to bore you guys to death.
But this is a really
good little chart to refer to and play around. You know, I'm not saying that if
you crave chocolate,
then you're deficient in magnesium 100%. Okay, but this is a really good kind
of code to go by
and to play around with. Like I said, your body has its own innate language.
Learn what it's trying
to tell you. So if you are craving things like bread, pasta and carbohydrates,
you might possibly,
and I'm not saying you are definitely, but you might possibly be deficient in
nitrogen
and a way to curb that craving is by consuming some nuts and beans and some ch
ia seeds as they're
high in nitrogen. So using this little table here might be really good to just
have a little play
around, add some of those foods to your diet or to your meals and see if it
really curbs that craving.
So oily and fatty foods, you might be deficient or low in omega-3 fatty acids
or calcium,
salty foods, it might be chloride, potassium, vitamin C. So you've got all of
those things down there
in the middle, which could be of possible deficiency. And then on the right,
you've got some great
alternatives to add into your diet or to even just swap out and try when you're
craving that food.
And notice if it does subside, then it could be a deficiency or a lacking of a
particular nutrient
or vitamin. And if it doesn't even touch the sides, take a look back at my
previous slides
and go, okay, so if I'm craving that food, could I potentially have a void or
be trying to soothe
an emotion or fulfill emotion or feel happy? It could be that it's not
necessarily deficiency
in nutrients or vitamins, it could be that you're trying to satisfy your brain
and emotions
in through food. And that's when earlier on, somewhere in your life at some
stage, without
even realising your brain's created, that connection between an emotion built
or a void of emotion
and the foods that were around you at that time. You know, it could be a parent
might have been
shouting at you. This is how random it could be, right? The parent could be
shouting at you
through at the back of the car. And someone gets into the car, you're at a
service station,
someone gets into the car with a bike or chips. It's the first thing that you
see, then you go
and reach most crisps. All of a sudden, you have then associated that feeling
of being disempowered,
feeling maybe fear, maybe being upset with that value, Chris. It's so, you know
, you don't realise
it when it's when it's making that connection. Beautiful. I feel like I didn't
finish that sentence,
but I did. Okay, conscious and central eating, because we all want to enjoy
food, that's why we're
here. So being present and eating with your senses is the best way to optimize
nutrient absorption,
decrease consumption and increase enjoyment. So what I mean is being present,
being around,
being conscious and eating with your senses, and I literally mean the five
senses that we have,
is a great way to increase that nutrient absorption. So you could be eating the
healthiest fucking
salad on the planet, but if you're stressed and you're thinking over there and
nothing, you know,
that you're not even thinking about the food and you're eating like this and
you're thinking away
and you're stressed, and that's not going to absorb well. It's going to sit in
your stomach.
You might have eaten something and afterwards you go, oh, that's really sat in
my stomach, you know,
that's not gone down. Your brain and your gut communicate and that's your body
telling you
that you weren't present, which is quite incredible that our body has this
language that we just haven't
tapped into that we haven't learned yet. So ways to be conscious and present,
you can eat until
you're 75% full. Why 75%? Because as soon as you get to that stage where you
have to unbutton your
top trousers, we've all done it. I do it when I go out almost all the time.
When you just have
to unbutton that top button and you're like, oh, I'm full. That is to the point
where your body is
going to have to work over time and you're not going to be able to absorb all
of that food,
and you've likely over eaten, you're going to feel a bit lethargic and tired.
Okay, when you eat 75%
capacity, that is when you feel alive, energized by food, as opposed to energ
ized by food.
Being conscious means that you acknowledge what foods you're choosing as fuel.
So going back to
pretty much like the first or second slide that I showed you about what
nutrition meant versus food,
acknowledge that the foods that you choose you are using as fuel. So if you're
putting in,
that you've probably had this analogy before, if you're putting a diesel into a
petrol car,
you ain't going to work. Whereas if you're putting petrol into a petrol car, it
's going to work.
It's going to work really bloody well. Okay, you can also slow your meal times
down. Slowing your
meal times down gives you much more presence, authority over what's happening
inside,
because you're giving your brain time to connect with your gut. Your gut's
going to say I'm full,
I'm still hungry, that was good, that wasn't so great, and you're really going
to be able to
create that authority over your body and put in exactly what you need. You can
start eating
when you're relaxed. So if we are stressed out, like I said, if you're stressed
out and things
aren't going well, maybe you're sad, you're in the sympathetic state. So you've
got two branches,
you've got your parasympathetic nervous system, and you've got your sympathetic
nervous system.
And when one is on, the other is off. When one is on parasympathetic nervous
system,
you are relaxing, you are digesting, you are calm. When you're stressed out,
that's switched off, and your sympathetic nervous system is on. Now that means
that you're stressed,
you're running around, probably like a headless chicken, you're picking up
after your kids,
you're hanging up, you're washing, and you're trying to eat your food at the
same time. That
is when you're not going to be able to digest your food, you're going to feel
tired. Again,
you're not going to feel energized, and you're not going to be able to digest,
and that's going to
make you feel bluh. It's not going to make you feel excited or happy to carry
on with your day,
or give you the energy that you need for the tasks ahead, which again then sets
you back
throughout the day. And you can eliminate distractions and negative gossip
around you,
because again, that's activating the stress response instead of activating the
relaxed
response, which is when we digest best. Beautiful. So how can we be sensual? So
sight.
Savor the rainbow colours of your food. Look at everything. The awesomeness of
nature's abundance
is beautiful, and all of which grows in the earth and is fed by the rain and
the sun. So
there's a huge connect there between the food that you're looking at, the
energy around you.
I don't know how woo-woo some of you are. Some of you might be. I'm not
completely woo-woo,
but I definitely agree in the energy that comes from things really goes through
.
It grows. It helps grow the food, and it helps fuel you. So look at the colours.
Look at that
beautiful texture and the food of the food that you're having. Smell your food.
So bring the food
close up to your nose. Smell it. Like just go for it. How often do you sit
there and bring the food
up and go and use your nose and your sense of smell, inhale so deeply so you
can smell and
save the flowers, the flavors. Touch what's the texture of your food. Use your,
you know,
maybe what's the texture of your utensils if you're using utensils or chop
sticks of the napkin
on your lap. Really zoom in to what's going on. It's conscious and essential
eating.
Environment. So this involves sight, smell and touch, but what the environment
you are creating
around yourself means to the way that you consume your food is quite important.
So when you eat
what's around you? Have you got candles on? Are you using your favourite dinner
plates? Are you
drinking out a fancy crystal instead of like a what bowl? When you eat your
meal, you're eating
your environment as well. So which is why eating while driving or when you're
at work on the go
can be really stressful because that environment, you're absorbing that as well
. So turn off all
phones, turn off the news because that is so depressing. Turn off your computer
,
switch your phone off or put it on silent, put it away and just enjoy the
presence of either
yourself or the other people that you're around. Again, enjoy the texture. Try
to your food about 30
times. This is basically unheard of and most people on average people do two
three times but
it's recommended that you chew every bite 30 times. So just notice the texture,
save the texture of the food. Let yourself breathe while eating, not many of us
inhale and exhale
while we're eating. All of this really creates that empowerment, that control
over what's happening
in our lives and ourselves. And yeah, pamper yourself. You might think but it's
just me at the dinner
table. This is only going to be me that's eating this. What's the point? Well,
who better to treat
to a luxury now? Who better? That's a good damn question. Okie dokie. So I want
you to be empowered
with nutrition. So just take again, there's only a couple of us on today. So I
will probably just
explain this task. And when you're re-watch in or later on, you're most welcome
to grab a piece
of paper and do this task yourself. So it's really important to focus on the
foods that work for you.
So you can feel empowered with nutrition rather than feeling like nutrition's
got a hold of you.
Ok? And that comes from eating the red light foods. So when you eat something,
if you feel lethargic,
if you feel tired or if you feel bored of eating it, or maybe it makes you feel
heavy or gross,
that's called your red light food. Ok? These can also include foods that you're
highly allergic to
or have an intolerance to because they don't leave you feeling great. So I want
you to take a
moment to list all of the foods that are on your red light. Now it doesn't mean
that you need to
avoid them at all costs. But just remember when you are consuming or about to
or want to consume
those foods, that they are a red light food. I want to make a note that I'm not
saying that this food
is bad or good because we then create those associations with bad and good with
punishment
and reward. And food is nutrition. It's not food, it's not this thing that we
need to use
as a social element or as a reward. We don't need to use it because the more
you create
that association with good and bad foods, the more you create a disconnect and
increase the
possibility of creating an eating disorder as well. So words weren't coming out
. Right, so then
you've got your amber foods. Make a list of foods that make you feel meh or
they might make you feel
comforted. They might make you feel ok, maybe a little bit happy but they might
be a bit
uninspiring. They might make you feel spotty or come out in spots or for me as
soon as I start
eating sugar, it goes right there and I see it and I don't feel happy. That's
my amber light.
That's my amber light food, sugars. And then I want you to take a moment to
write all of the
green light foods. Now this is most likely going to be the biggest list that
you're going to make.
Foods that make you feel energetic, foods that make you feel happy and
encouraged,
foods that make you feel yeah, I'm being healthy. I am feeding myself with
exactly the fuel that I
need, with the nutrition that I need. Foods that make you feel beautiful and
healthy.
Every one of your lists is going to be slightly different. There's no right or
wrong to this
because it's your body's natural language. So take a moment now and do this
task for you ladies
that are watching now. Sorry, you don't have to come back. Beautiful. So a
quick do and don't
with being empowered with nutrition. Do focus on foods that you get to have. So
switch the narrative.
I'm going to go back quickly. That's the green light foods guys. The foods that
you do get to have
focus on those. Don't focus on that red list of foods that you can't have or
that you don't
that you shouldn't be having. Look at the abundant green list and I can
guarantee you if you wrote
down every single fruit, vegetable, green, grain, nuts, legumes, seeds,
whatever, everything that
makes you feel energetic and happy and positive, it's going to be a lot bigger
than the red list.
If it's not, let's have a chat. Do eat the foods that have you feel empowered
again,
your green light foods and help you reach your goals. Do give yourself
realistic and achievable
goals. This is the problem with pretty much everything in life nowadays as we
go. Okay,
this is my goal and we feel very disappointed when we don't get there because
we have not set
ourselves a realistic or achievable goal. We set ourselves up for failure. Set
yourself up for
success. I'm going to lose two pounds in three weeks. Something that's much
more achievable.
Okay, and celebrate. Do celebrate yourself at every single god damn win because
girl,
you fucking deserve it. We do not celebrate ourselves enough. Nobody does. So
if you chose to
do something, if you followed the nada that I talked about earlier and you were
able to
change a pattern or change a behaviour or change a habit positively, celebrate
it.
If it means that you reached two inches to the left for an apple instead of two
inches to the right,
which was a packet of biscuits, celebrate that. So that was a good job and
write it down. Write
down every single win because these will mount up and when you're feeling low,
look at that list
of amazing things, amazing choices that you have done and you will feel so much
more empowered.
It's like when people tell us to write down what we're grateful for, it makes
us feel empowered
because we're like, wow, we have a lot of stuff in our life. Okay, don't think
that there are
foods that you can't have unless you're definitely allergic, of course. The red
light foods are
red light foods. They're not bad. It's not that you can't have them. It's just
that they don't
make you feel as empowered and we want to be the strong bad ass bitch that we
are. Okay.
Yes, I said that. Don't use terms such as good and bad foods. Again, as I
mentioned,
that creates a negative association. Don't give yourself a goal that's not
achievable for you
right now, which is the opposite to what I've written there. Don't use food or
negative words
as punishment if things don't go to plant. So often we'll say, if I don't lose
weight,
then I'm going to have to starve myself or I'm going to have to eat kale salads
.
To me, that sounds great because I'm strange, but you know, I'm going to have
to eat kale salads
for the rest of the week. Don't use that as punishment. Do, however, use
awesome and
positive things and actions and rewards in your life for doing well. So reward
yourself with
going to see your best friend, going for a tea or a coffee ketchup, but going
for a walk along the
beach for spending an extra 10 minutes on yourself, something that's positive,
something that builds
excitement and helps you feeling empowered. Beautiful. So I told you there wasn
't a huge amount
about vegan and plant-based eating, but why a plant-based lifestyle is so
empowering is for
many reasons, but for the animals. Imagine you yourself get to save a billion
animals in your
life. That's incredible. And it happens literally with every person that goes
plant-based saves,
I think, why is it? I did it. I should have written it down here. There's
actually a website that
shows you how many animals that you would save if you went plant-based now or
vegan now. So you can
save billions of animals' lives. You can help contribute towards the planet and
towards saving
the planet. And I know that it's probably over the edge by now and probably not
going to do much,
but you will. Your impact is going to have a huge impact down the line. Your
decision,
sorry, is going to have a huge impact down the line. For your pocket, because
being plant-based,
believe it or not, if actually really freaking cheap, I basically bought my
protein for the next
three weeks at £2.19. Tell me what packets of chicken breasts will last me
three weeks,
put £2.90. It can be cheap. And if that's something that you are interested in
doing,
plant-based on the cheap, let me know, for your health and longevity. Like I
mentioned, you can
prevent reverse and reduce illness and disease, like cancer, diabetes, obesity,
you can slow aging. It promotes more energy, faster recovery, stronger gut,
increased immunity,
and bone health. And again, imagine having the authority and power over doing
that for yourself.
That's incredible. And you can manage your own weight and mental health, which
I didn't write
on there, but weight and mental health consistently. And that is very important
, especially in 2022.
So my quick top tips for going plant-based, focus on everything you get to have
. Again,
look at your green-like foods. Have your green-like foods listed somewhere,
maybe on a fridge.
Have all of the things that you get to have, because as soon as you take the
focus off what you can't
have, you put the focus on what you can have and where your energy goes. What's
the saying?
My brain's gone to mashed potato. Wherever you focus, your energy is going to
go.
Your attention? Yeah, where your attention goes, anything close.
Thank you. Yeah, so where your attention goes, energy flows. So as soon as you
start focusing on
all of the possible, all of the things that are possible, all of the things
that you get to have,
then you are in that positive mindset as opposed to going, "Oh, I can't have
this. Oh, but I can't
have that." It's such a different vibe. It's such a different energy. If you
talk to someone and
you say, "Oh, hey, so what you have been having for dinner?" And they turn
around and say,
"Well, I can't have me. I can't have derring. I can't have four." They turn
"Well, I can have red lentils. I can have green lentils. I can have tofu. I can
have tempeh.
I can have chickpeas." How different is that conversation? It's such a shift in
energy in your
bill. Be so much more empowered to make the right decisions for you if you
focus on the green
light foods, if you focus on everything that you get to have. Another top tip
is just to start
slow. Everyone jumps in at the deep end, not everyone, but some people jump in
at the deep end,
and then they get really bad cramps. They get bad flatulence. They are really
struggling on a day
to day. Well, because you have just started eating something that your gut is
not used to,
your gut has not built the bacteria inside it to be able to digest properly.
You need to give
your body time to adjust. Start slow. Do your research. It is very, very
important that if you do this,
if you jump ship and go plant-based straight away, that you do a little bit of
research,
not only for your body, but also for your mind. You're not going to be thrown
left, right and
centre and feel overwhelmed with all of this information. Your research can be
me, so if you
have any questions, come to me. Eat as whole as possible. So little, that means
consuming little
or little to know refined or processed foods. This is going to increase your
nutrient intake.
It's going to increase your satiation. It's going to increase the bio
availability in your gut,
which again means that your gut is going to be much stronger. It's just going
to be more
beneficial. It's going to give you more energy as well. It's going to make you
feel more focused
because you're increasing the nutrients basically. Eating as whole as possible
reduces the amount
of processed foods, which is calorie-high, but nutrient-low. So if that doesn't
really make sense,
you're welcome to chat with me later. Then consume as many varieties as
possible. Again,
all different fruits and veg have different compounds. They have different
antioxidants.
They have different nutrients and vitamins and minerals inside them. So if you
eat as
big a variety as possible, you are going to consume most of what you need. If
you just stick to
one broccoli, one vegetable like broccoli, one grain like rice, and one protein
like tofu,
yeah, that would be great. But you won't get the nutrients and then you'll end
up becoming
deficient. Finally, find a supportive community. Find a family member or a
friend who will support
you because you'll need someone to talk to. You'll need someone to taste your
food. You'll need
someone to make sure you're okay. And so find someone that you can trust. I
thought that was it.
Sorry, nearly there. I think this is the second to last slide.
Chips were going plant-based. Eat these daily. Fruits, especially berries. You
've got your
examples down there, so you can screenshot this while I'm talking. Leafy green
and cruciferous
vegetables, nuts and seeds, herbs and spices, especially ginger and turmeric.
They are like the
powerhouse onion and garlic, beans and legames. Try and complete these daily
and that will cover
your variety that I talked about. Again, if you want to screenshot that,
please, by all means. So empowerment through nutrition, fundamentals. Listen to
and learn.
No, listen to and learn to understand. It does make sense to understand your
body's natural
language. So just learn, listen and play around. Figure out what it's talking
about. Take a moment.
Take a step back. Take time out to journal or to think about what it could be
telling you.
Take empowered action on what it is telling you. Sort, sleep, stress or
movement activities before
food for comfort or for avoiding emotions or presence. So often we will feel
the emotions that we're lacking with food. So if you try and increase your
sleep,
as we were talking about earlier in Sammy, increase your stress-reducing
activities,
or if you move a little bit more before you look for food to fulfil this,
if you find those first, oh my god, my brain is not too much. If you find those
first and fill those
in, then you are less likely to feel disempowered by overeating or eating the
wrong foods.
Eat foods that make you feel fabulous, not tired or bloated, so green light,
not red light.
Learn how to fix and heal yourself through empowered action. So of course with
the supervision of a
doctor of course, but yeah, you should be able to learn how to fix and heal
yourself through
nutrition and through empowered action. Take ownership of your body, your
behaviours and your
mind. Feed your body and soul with high energy, high frequency foods, like a
whole plant-based
food diet. That's me. Finally, I've finished talking now, I promise you. Um, I
do have any
questions? Anyone have any questions? Um, do you have any questions? I don't
have any questions,
but yeah, if that was anything, I'd keep the answer. I don't have any questions
, but I wonder if
I could talk to you maybe after or some kind of link that I could gain contact
with you further
about all of this. Sorry, Sammy. So that again, it was a little bit disturbed.
I just said, um,
I don't have any questions right now, but I wondered if there was a link or
something that I could
contact you like later on, um, about speaking more about everything. We can put
it in the WhatsApp
group, Sammy. We'll put it in the call for anyone that's watching back tomorrow
or whatever as well.
Thank you. It was amazing. So good. Thank you so much. Thank you so much, Sammy
. No problem at all.
I look forward to chatting with you and having a little play around with your
sleep and figuring
out exactly what's going on. Yeah. Thank you. It's amazing. Really, really
loved it.
I've got a question. Oh, you're most welcome. And so I still can't see anyone's
faces. This is
really nice. So I was going to ask about, because I feel like I am a conscious
person in most things
and good, but I feel like I have this monthly cycle where I come off the wagon
every month and
obviously, along with my cycle, I have these few days where I find it really, a
really hard task to
be mindful and be huge. Um, do you have any tips for that? What would you say?
But like tackling,
because it feels very different, a craving, like a menstrual craving feels very
different from a
normal one. Oh, yes. Um, so absolutely nourish that. Take pair of your body. We
are not
freaking machines like we think we are. And I am guilty of this. I am so guilty
of feeling down
if I haven't worked out at the gym, you know, if I've eaten more because it's
that time of the month.
If it is a cycle and it keeps coming up around the same time of the month,
regardless of whether
it is when you are bleeding beforehand afterwards, if it is roughly around the
same time, then you
know it's to do with your menstrual cycle, right? Give yourself grace. Give
yourself space.
Don't be hard on yourself because after all, we are human. We operate totally
different to men.
All nutrition, most nutrition studies, sorry, have been based and used male
participants.
So there's not a huge amount of research out there that suggests that, you know
, that we're
overeating or anything like that. When we come lead up to our period and when
we do bleed,
we require more energy. We become hotter. Our body temperature increases, right
? Just that,
just your body temperature increasing, you are burning more calories. Therefore
, you are going
to feel hungrier. You're bleeding. So you're losing a lot of iron. So give
yourself that grace.
Know that it is, you know, a regular occurrence and it is okay and just bring
it back afterwards.
And again, don't use that punishment kind of cycle, but just consume more of
those green light foods
afterwards and as much of them as you can throughout that time where you feel
like you might be a
little bit weaker or that you might be more partial to a piece of cake.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that makes sense. Yeah, totally. Yeah, I think that I
probably
need to eat more carbs around that time because they have a very low carb diet
anyway.
So probably just need to do that before they possibly kick it.
Finging on like sugar or whatever.
Yeah, absolutely. And you know, if you do crave carbs and you have a low carb
diet,
start off by feeding yourself with all of the healthy carbohydrates, right?
Utilize sweet potatoes, regular potatoes. Don't be scared of regular potatoes,
beans and legumes. These are high in carbohydrates, but they don't have, they
won't have the same effect on your blood sugar levels as a cake wheel. So if
you fill up your
meals with high healthy whole carbohydrates like grains, potatoes, legumes,
beans, then
that might give you a little bit of a balance there for afterwards and you
might crave those
sweet foods less because you already have had that insulin spike from the
carbohydrates.
Does that make sense? Yeah, yeah, totally. Yeah, thank you.
You're most welcome. So just while I'm here quickly, I mentioned about the free
bie and the
offer. Do you mind if I just quickly explain that? So I have a three seven day
plant based
meal guide. So if you're interested in going plant based and you're like, where
do I start?
Because that was me. I created a 28 day meal plan. I use this month after month
after month.
So I stick to it. It's got breakfast, lunch, dinner, mid morning snack and
afternoon snack
if you're still hungry. So there's so many options, but each week is
specifically curated
and designed. So you get the variety that I was talking about. So you don't
waste food. So you
get variety and that it's not too far fetched. So I'm not having you eat a
salad every single day
and it'd be like, whoa, okay, this plant based eating. Like, for example, one
of the meals on
there is a curry, one of them on there is spaghetti bolognese and one of them
is mac and cheese.
I mean, they don't necessarily jump out as vegan to you. So it's not too far
fetched
and there's a lot of ideas and it's very versatile. So if you want the 28 days,
the girls will be giving you the link for the 28 day meal plan for 28 pounds.
Okay, so 28 days
for 28 pounds for ignoring. So 28 day meal plan for 28 day for 28 pounds.
Otherwise,
if you just want a taster of what it's like, I've got the free seven day meal
plan. The 28 days
for 28 pounds is pretty extensive. There's like, there's video trainings in
there. There's mindset
shift training. There's kitchen training. There's a meal planning generator in
there. So not only
after the whole month of meals, if you are still bored of that, the meal
planning generator will
help you create plant based meals time and time again and different each time
and it will help you
use ingredients that you already have or that you need to use up as well. So
the 28 day meal plan
is very expensive. There's a lot going on in there. And like me and Sammy are
going to do,
we're going to jump on a call. So I'll have a 15, a free 15 minute triage call
with anyone
if you are interested in learning about how I might be able to help you. It's
not a sales call.
I just want to put that out there. I'm literally just offering you 15 minutes
to figure out if
there is a way or means that I can help you get to your goals. That's it. Oh
yeah, Instagram and
Facebook. I'm at overhaul hw the hw stands for health and wellness. So overhaul
hw at the bottom
of the screen. There's my website and my email address there as well. Thank you
. Thank you so much.
Thank you so much Bianco. We so appreciate you coming and doing this for us.
And I know we had
some technical difficulties. So I'm so sorry guys that was totally my fault.
Thank you so much for
coming back. And I know that a lot of the girls are really going to appreciate
all this guidance
that you've given. So I'll keep it good on what people are saying when they're
watching it back.
I'll post in the WhatsApp with your contact details as well. And yeah, thank
you so much. Really
enjoyed it. That was amazing. Thank you. You are most, most welcome. Thank you
so much. I think
no God. Don't tell me it's my in that collection as well. Beautiful. All right.
You're recording
aren't you? So yeah, I will send you through all of my links and the girls will
be able to send you
folks everything that you need. And if it's not on there, just contact me and
say I need this.
Absolutely. Yes. We'll be in touch with you anyway. Thank you so much. Have an
amazing weekend.
Thank you very much. We'll see you soon. See ya. Bye. Bye guys. Bye. Bye. Bye.